<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joe Jean</title><link href="http://www.joejean.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.joejean.net/feeds/communication-technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.joejean.net/</id><updated>2015-11-09T06:24:00+04:00</updated><entry><title>A small experiment on Stack Exchange Expatriate</title><link href="http://www.joejean.net/articles/experiment-on-stack-exchange-expatriate/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-09T06:24:00+04:00</published><updated>2015-11-09T06:24:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Jean</name></author><id>tag:www.joejean.net,2015-11-09:articles/experiment-on-stack-exchange-expatriate/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a programmer I use Stack Overflow a lot. But last week one of my professors asked us to pick one of the Stack Exchange websites that we have never used before and experiment with it by using some of its features. This article is an analysis of my experience with Stack Exchange Expatriates. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did I pick Stack Exchange Expatriates? Well, I wanted to pick something non technical as I already have a lot of experiences with technical forums such as &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/"&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions"&gt;SubReddit cscareerquestions&lt;/a&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After signing up for Stack Exchange Expatriates and as I was going through the questions I saw a rather simple question which nobody had answered yet. The question which you can see in the screen shot below looked somewhat simple to me. Simple in the sense that a Google search would have revealed the answer. So I decided to try to answer it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src ="http://www.joejean.net/images/stackexchange.png" class="img-responsive img-rounded" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I naturally went ahead and tried two or three Google queries until I stumbled upon an &lt;a href="http://www.h1bwiki.com/h-1b-amendment-requirements/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, on a website specialized in H1B information, that has the answer to the question. At this point I paused for a while to think about the credibility of the source of the information. I did that because according to my experience, there is a lot of false information on the WEB especially when it comes to those specialized topics. Among other things, I checked the comments at the bottom of the article and most commenters except one seemed to validate the correctness of the information provided in the article. But can those users also be trusted? I had no answer to that. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After investigating I decided that I could trust the content of the article with a confidence level of about 70%. Therefore, I went back to the Stack Exchange Expatriates and answer the question by quoting the article and putting a link to it as well. Referencing one's source when replying to a question on Stack Exchange is highly encouraged in their guidelines. To me, by referencing the original source, I was not only following proper standards but I was also passing on the responsibility of verifying the correctness of the information to the original poster. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After answering the question I couldn't help but wonder why didn't the original poster do the same thing I did to find the answer. Maybe he did but he did not use the right queries hence why he did not get the answer. Or maybe he did not even bother to do a Google search first knowing that a Stack Exchange user who wants more points would be happy to do the research and give him a solution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of points, so far I have only received one vote for my answer and the original poster asked some follow-up questions and another user had answered before I could get my hands on them. I have no idea why the original poster did not mark my answer as the accepted one, which would have resulted in more points for me. But why do I care about earning more points?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, points seem to be a very important part of the experience a user can have on a Stack Exchange site. The number of points you have can determine whether you have access to certain features of the site or not. For example, I saw a question with an already accepted answer and tried to up-vote but I get a message saying that I need 50 more points for my vote to count. I'm assuming that the people who designed Stack Exchange have a good rationale to support such restrictions. Since I don't know what their rationales are I'm not going to criticize the feature. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that this experience got me to think about is how much redundancy of information there is on the web. The same information is repeated in different places on the web. I know that storage is becoming cheaper and cheaper but I wonder whether the such redundancy has any other cost that we haven't discovered. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tech"></category><category term="communication"></category></entry><entry><title>Describing some aspect of life in my hometown with three emojis</title><link href="http://www.joejean.net/articles/emojis-for-cap-haitien/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-28T06:24:00+04:00</published><updated>2015-09-28T06:24:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Jean</name></author><id>tag:www.joejean.net,2015-09-28:articles/emojis-for-cap-haitien/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was tasked to make three conceptual emojis that describe or represent an aspect of life in your hometown. In this post I talk about the approach I followed to come up with the design. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I'm from Cap-Haitien which is the second city in Haiti. I was born and raised there, so I know a lot about the city. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to come up with the initial emoji designs, I had to think about three things that are part of the traditions and culture of my hometown. More than three things came to mind. Therefore, I had to select three of them: the attachment and pride that is cultivated by the native of this city -- in French we call it 'La Fierte Christophienne', our love for pumpkin soup, and our most popular greeting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After selecting the topics I wanted the emojis to represent, I needed to come up with an actual design for each of those topics. For that I used an android app called "Emojidom Maker". It is a simple and easy to use app that lets one create some cool emojis. For someone who is not that skilled in using sophisticated design like me, the app was a  lifesaver.  After some tweaking and playing around with the app, I came up with the following designs to represent respectively the concept of attachment and pride cutivated by the native of Cap-Haitien, our love for pumpkin soup, and our most popular greeting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/i1zj7ehv1zwb0zz/okap.png?dl=0"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/1ck4pmc7l1vms4r/joumou.png?dl=0"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/nqz3rewpjewcvha/sakpase.png?dl=0"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then shared those designs with my brother and two of my friends--who are currently living there-- and asked them for feedback. My friends said they love them and one of them especially really like the pumpkin emoji. On the other hand my brother suggested that I remove the little read hearts from it. He also said the greeting emoji would be nicer with some additional color. And there was no criticism on the first emoji. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I went back to Emojidom Maker and I made some changes to address the feedback I received on the first versions. I only made changes to the last two emojis. I removed the little hearts from the pumpkin emoji and I also added a little bit of color to the greeting emoji. The final versions are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/i1zj7ehv1zwb0zz/okap.png?dl=0"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/v5e33arwzm2q4ib/joumou_2.png?dl=0"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/o5w6oczrgo8wgqh/sakpase_2.png?dl=0"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also sent those designs to three other friends of which only one of them said he did not like the pumpkin emoji because he personally does not like pumpkin soup anyways. The two other friends loved them. And they asked me if there was a way they could install them on their phone in order to use them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess, that's gonna be the third step in this project.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tech"></category><category term="communication"></category></entry><entry><title>I had a 12-hour technology detox, here is how it went</title><link href="http://www.joejean.net/articles/12-hour-technology-detox/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-15T06:24:00+04:00</published><updated>2015-09-15T06:24:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Jean</name></author><id>tag:www.joejean.net,2015-09-15:articles/12-hour-technology-detox/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On September 13th 2015, from 12:00pm to 12:00am I was on a technology detox , i.e. I was not allowed to use any electronic communication devices. The following is an account of how I spent those twelve hours. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting my 12-hour technology detox, I had to warn my friends and family about it. I felt the need to do so because I usually reply quickly to emails and instant messages except when I'm traveling. And I did not want anyone to start panicking when, suddenly, I become unreachable for 12 straight hours. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also selected a couple of things to read. One of them is a book by Viktor Frankl called "Man's search for meaning". In addition to that I printed out the articles "A template engine" and "Git from the bottom Up"
. I figured if I'm not gonna have access to my technology devices for 12 hours I'd better have an alternative. And reading physical copies of books and articles was one of those alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this preparation out of the way, I was ready to start the journey. At 11:55am I turned off my laptop and my phone and stored them away. At 12:00pm I headed to the dining hall where I was supposed to eat lunch with a friend a little later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While waiting in the dining hall, since I did not have my phone to play with, I started reading Viktor's book. A couple of pages into the book, I read "A man could get used to anything". I then paused and thought "man, I have so gotten used to being always connected through my devices. Would it be possible to get used to living without this constant connection to information?". Then I went back to my reading. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At around 12:45pm, my friend showed up (by the way, I could still tell the exact timing of things because I was wearing a nice analog watch). We grabbed food, started eating and then 'bam', he received a notification on his phone. He naturally pulled his phone, checked the message and placed it back on the table. During the short time this was happening, the urge to also check my phone too suddenly came to me. I was thinking that I may have a new email or a new WhatsApp message from one of my friends. But I couldn't do it because my phone was away :). This made me aware of the fact that  usually I would be constantly checking my phone while eating with a group of friends. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After eating lunch, I continued reading the book. Then I went back to my room to take a nap. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I woke up at 3:10pm and started documenting the experience. Well, this is the first time in in about four years that I have to write that much on paper. One thing I notice is that even though I'm using a pencil I tend to erase less than I would hit backspace when I'm typing on on my computer. And I think that's a great thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 6:45, I got back to my room after eating dinner. Before going to dinner, I had been quiet productive. I did the reading for my statistics class and I talked and interacted with people way more than I would if I had access to my phone and my computer. But every once in a while the urge to check my email or Hacker News or Reddit would come to me and then disappear after a few minutes. Sometimes I would unconsciously put my hands in my pocket trying to pull my phone out thinking that it is there as usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 6:45 and midnight, I did some more reading, went for a walk, started my homework and engaged in some interesting conversations with other students. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then at midnight, I turned on my phone and my computer. I checked my email and found out that I had missed a 3-hour on-campus work assignment. This happened because I did not have my phone with me to remind me of it. Fortunately my supervisor was really understanding so I did not get a blame letter or something. And I think this revealed how dependent my everyday life is on technology. I thought about how I would not have missed my work assignment if I had a printed version of my calendar on my wall.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tech"></category><category term="communication"></category></entry><entry><title>On communication and technology</title><link href="http://www.joejean.net/articles/on-communication-and-technology/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-08T09:07:00+04:00</published><updated>2015-09-08T09:07:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Jean</name></author><id>tag:www.joejean.net,2015-09-08:articles/on-communication-and-technology/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As human beings we have a natural need to communicate with one another. In order to do so, we use different tools. Such tools include language, gestures, drums, computers,
 cellphones etc...
To me all those tools that facilitate communication among humans are technologies. In a more general sense, a technology is anything that improves the life of humans. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first chapter of the book &lt;em&gt;"The Information"&lt;/em&gt; by James Gleick we see how the same technology can be used differently in different cultures. The author tells how the drum is used in sub-Saharan Africa as a tool to share information --many sentences-- over a long distance. But this was a big surprise to Europeans who were living in sub-Saharan Africa at the time. In their culture the best they could do with the drum was transferring a set of one-word long messages such as &lt;em&gt;attack, retreat...&lt;/em&gt;. This anecdote reminds me of how versatile a technological tool can be. How a certain technology is used is up to the creativity and imagination of whoever is using it. This makes me wonder, do we, as humans, always use technology in way that makes us better? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, in &lt;em&gt;"The Machine Stops"&lt;/em&gt; by Edward M. Forster, we see how human beings became too dependent on technology. Face to face interactions are almost non-existent and the humans use technology for everything in our life. It is like they are living in a virtual world. People have friends they have never met in person. I personally sometimes would send a Facebook message to my roommate who is just sitting in the living room while I'm laying in bed in the bedroom. While some might consider this an efficient way of communicating, I do think that, as human beings, we definitely need more direct and physical interactions. Sometimes it definitely makes sense and is more   convenient and efficient to use technology to communicate. For example, it is so convenient for two people who are located thousands of miles apart from each other to communicate via email or Skype etc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think human beings need to strive to find the right balance between using technology to communicate and having real interactions. It is so easy to always resort to technology whenever we need to communicate with someone else, but if we pause a second and ask ourselves “can this be done in person” we realize that technology is not always needed for us to communicate.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tech"></category><category term="communication"></category></entry></feed>