<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Articles on Joe Jean | Software Engineer</title>
    <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Articles on Joe Jean | Software Engineer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.joejean.net/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Automating The Deployment of a Codeigniter/PHP Website with Deployer</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/automating-the-deployment-of-a-codeigniter-php-website-with-deployer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/automating-the-deployment-of-a-codeigniter-php-website-with-deployer/</guid>
      <description>About 4 months ago, I started using some of my free time to help build Labocine.com, an amazing new platform for science cinema. The back-end is written using the PHP framework Codeigniter. Being at its early stage, the site was hosted on one of those traditional hosting providers. And the deployment of new features was done using the traditional ftp approach. After joining the project and as it grew, I decided to host it on a VPS and automate the deployment process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Two Weeks At Namshi</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-first-two-weeks-at-namshi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-first-two-weeks-at-namshi/</guid>
      <description>On July 10th, I joined Namshi as a Junior Software Engineer. I was really excited to start my first full time job writing software. Though, I have to confess that I was also a bit afraid and nervous. Fortunately, after just two days working with the team the fear and nervousness went away. In this post, I will share with you some of the things I have learned so far as well as what I love about working in this awesome team.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speed and Usability Performance of Top UAE Websites.</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/speed-and-usability-performance-of-top-uae-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/speed-and-usability-performance-of-top-uae-websites/</guid>
      <description>Google recently pusblished a new version of their PageSpeed API. I wanted to play around with it a bit. So, I decided to build a page that displays a visualization of the speed of some of the most popular UAE websites.
I went to Alexa in order to gather the data about the most popular websites in the UAE. I also added a few sites that were not on Alexa&amp;rsquo;s list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning new tools by implementing the same project using different languages/frameworks.</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/learning-new-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/learning-new-tools/</guid>
      <description>I’m always looking for ways to improve my technical skills. And one thing that I hear a lot as advice to software developers is to keep trying new tools and frameworks. So, I have decided to try a couple of languages/frameworks that I either have never used before or have little experience with. The best way for me to do that is by building the same application using those different languages/frameworks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A small experiment on Stack Exchange Expatriate</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/experiment-on-stack-exchange-expatriate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/experiment-on-stack-exchange-expatriate/</guid>
      <description>As a programmer I use Stack Overflow a lot. But last week one of my professors asked us to pick one of the Stack Exchange websites that we have never used before and experiment with it by using some of its features. This article is an analysis of my experience with Stack Exchange Expatriates.
Why did I pick Stack Exchange Expatriates? Well, I wanted to pick something non technical as I already have a lot of experiences with technical forums such as Stack Overflow, Hacker News, SubReddit cscareerquestions etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving My Personal Website from Heroku to Github Pages</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/deploying-my-personal-website-to-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/deploying-my-personal-website-to-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>When I first built my personal website I deployed it to Heroku. At that time Heroku was the best option for me because it offered a free tier and it was relatively easy to use. But one thing I did not like about it was that the application dyno&amp;mdash;the container that handles all the HTTP traffic to the site&amp;mdash; would go to sleep if my website receives no traffic in a 30-minute period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Describing some aspect of life in my hometown with three emojis</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/emojis-for-cap-haitien/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/emojis-for-cap-haitien/</guid>
      <description>I was tasked to make three conceptual emojis that describe or represent an aspect of life in your hometown. In this post I talk about the approach I followed to come up with the design.
Firstly, I&amp;rsquo;m from Cap-Haitien which is the second city in Haiti. I was born and raised there, so I know a lot about the city.
In order to come up with the initial emoji designs, I had to think about three things that are part of the traditions and culture of my hometown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I had a 12-hour technology detox, here is how it went</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/12-hour-technology-detox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/12-hour-technology-detox/</guid>
      <description>On September 13th 2015, from 12:00pm to 12:00am I was on a technology detox , i.e. I was not allowed to use any electronic communication devices. The following is an account of how I spent those twelve hours.
Before starting my 12-hour technology detox, I had to warn my friends and family about it. I felt the need to do so because I usually reply quickly to emails and instant messages except when I&amp;rsquo;m traveling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On communication and technology</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/on-communication-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/on-communication-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>As human beings we have a natural need to communicate with one another. In order to do so, we use different tools. Such tools include language, gestures, drums, computers, cellphones etc&amp;hellip; To me all those tools that facilitate communication among humans are technologies. In a more general sense, a technology is anything that improves the life of humans.
In the first chapter of the book &amp;ldquo;The Information&amp;rdquo; by James Gleick we see how the same technology can be used differently in different cultures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is your Python loop followed by an else clause? If yes, read on</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/else-clause-in-python-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/else-clause-in-python-loop/</guid>
      <description>Today I decided to start my day by reading about common anti-patterns in Python and how to fix them. An anti-pattern in the context of programming is a piece of code that solves a problem but that has the potential of having unintended bad consequences.
One of those anti-patterns is the use of an else clause right after a loop without a break statement. As the article explains, the else clause following a loop is only executed when the loop sequence becomes empty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Week At the Recurse Center</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/first-week-at-recurse-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/first-week-at-recurse-center/</guid>
      <description>This summer I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to be attending the Recurse Center (RC). RC is a 12-week long self-directed retreat for programmers. It is a place one goes to become a better programmer by working on programming projects of one&amp;rsquo;s interest.
We started the first day, Monday the 26th of May, with some welcome talks by the RC founders, facilitators and employees. The Recursers from the first batch also gave us some really good advices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery make life easier</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/continuous-integration-and-continuous-delivery-make-my-life-easier/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/continuous-integration-and-continuous-delivery-make-my-life-easier/</guid>
      <description>I have been hearing the terms &amp;ldquo;continuous integration&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;continuous delivery&amp;rdquo; for quite some time. However, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until last week that I decided to not only learn more about them but also use them in my own projects.
What is continuous integration? Continuous integration (CI) is a development practice where developers push code to a central repository several times a day. Every time code is pushed to the repository an automated build is run to verify that the new code did not cause any errors/bugs in the system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Mashups Class] My Final Project</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-final-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-final-project/</guid>
      <description>For my final project I decided to build something that I myself needed: a motivational quote API. For quite some time I had been searching the web for a quotes API and I was not able to find anything interesting, so I built one.
I did not have any quotes. So I scraped this webpage which contains a list of 150 inspirational quotes. Then I created a database with those quotes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Mashups Class] Ideas for Second Project</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/ideas-for-second-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/ideas-for-second-project/</guid>
      <description>For my second project for this class, I have two ideas. I would like to implement one during this week and work on the other when I have more free time. Okay, without further ado here they are.
The first idea is to create an interactive map that represents the countries where the NYUAD student body hails from. To implement this idea, I would need a dataset of all the countries represented in the student body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Mashups Class] My Favorite Class Materials So Far</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-favorite-class-materials-so-far/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-favorite-class-materials-so-far/</guid>
      <description>I can&amp;rsquo;t believe we are already in the middle of this great class, in fact one of my favorite so far. Over the past weeks, we have used a lot of great tutorials/videos and articles as learning materials for the class. All of them were really great. Below is a list of some of my favorites in no particular order.
 Importance of Color, Font, and Icons: This article provides great tips on how to use colors, font and icons when designing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Mashups Class] First Project: San Francisco Graffiti Explorer</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/first-project-san-francisco-graffiti-explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/first-project-san-francisco-graffiti-explorer/</guid>
      <description>For my first project for the Mashups class , I built a website &amp;ndash;available here&amp;ndash; that allows the user to explore graffiti spots in San Fransisco. In this article, I&amp;rsquo;m going to provide some details on how I went about building the project.
First of all, let me tell you some of the tools I used in this project. I used the graffiti dataset from DataSF. This data set provides information&amp;ndash;including geographic coordinates, status, and a photo when available&amp;ndash; about graffiti cases reported in the San Francisco area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Mashups Class] How to set a default value for a function&#39;s parameter in Javascript &amp; first project idea</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/how-to-set-default-value-for-function-parameter-in-javascript/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/how-to-set-default-value-for-function-parameter-in-javascript/</guid>
      <description>This week my homework has two parts. In the first part, I have to solve the three exercises found at the end of chapter two in the book Eloquent Javascript.In the second part, I have to describe what I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about doing for my first single page app project, how the data flow might work, and what the experience of a user visiting the site would be like.
How to set a default value for function parameter in Javascript The first exercise was to write a loop that makes seven calls to console.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Mashups Class] Playing with an open API</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/playing-with-an-open-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/playing-with-an-open-api/</guid>
      <description>As part of my first homework for Mashups: Creating with web API, I had to first find, post and describe an API that returns JSON data.
Initial Plan After playing around with a couple of APIs, I decided to use the World Bank API. I like the fact that one does not need a key to make requests to this API. And I also found the documentation to be clear and useful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to run Python 2 and Python 3 together on Windows 7</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/how-to-run-python-2-and-python-3-together-on-windows-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/how-to-run-python-2-and-python-3-together-on-windows-7/</guid>
      <description>I have always wanted to have both Python 2 and Python 3 installed and running on my Windows 7 computer, but I feared that installation was going to be a nightmare. However, today I put my fear aside and dove right into the task.
At least two scenarios are possible. While my experience was with the first scenario, the second one is also possible. So here is how to approach each one: ###Scenario 1: Python 2, virtualenv and virtualenvwrapper are already installed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My method for finding the best books on any topic of</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-method-for-finding-the-best-books-on-any-topic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/my-method-for-finding-the-best-books-on-any-topic/</guid>
      <description>I recently read an article about the importance of Computational Thinking. It is important because it helps you think about ways you can use computers to solve problems &amp;ndash; something that the knowledge of a programming language&amp;rsquo;s syntax does not necessarily provide. So, I decided to read a good book about the subject. But first, I had to find the book. In what follows, I will explain how I went about finding a great Computational Thinking book using Amazon and users&amp;rsquo; feedback.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Tips for writing more concise and elegant code in Python</title>
      <link>https://www.joejean.net/articles/5-tips-for-writing-more-concise-elegant-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.joejean.net/articles/5-tips-for-writing-more-concise-elegant-python/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I was reviewing some of the first lines of code I wrote when I was learning python three years ago. While they worked, I now realise that there are many things I could have done in a more elegant and concise way. Of course, when learning a new programming language one is always encouraged to build things from scratch, to write one&amp;rsquo;s own functions, classes or methods to do things even when such code might already exists.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>